Start recording.
Share screen.
Screen.
All right.
How's the
concept?
>> It's good for me.
>> Bigger.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, it's good.
>> A little bit bigger for me.
Think enough?
>> Yep.
>> Okay.
So, we were going to talk about state
charts
as soon as my intelliges. There we go.
Wow.
Okay.
All right. So, the first thing that I
want to do is just give you a quick
overview of the basic state charts
ideas.
I don't know if I want to bother with
tests or anything else. Is that still
the same zoom level?
>> All right. So
as most of you already kind of know, I
tend in functional programming, I tend
to build programs uh as much as possible
with the philosophy that most of you are
used to and know of immutable value pure
functions. Um whatever you can do with
that, do that. Um and so folklore for
example, the state map is an immutable
value and mutations take that from one
state of the world to the next state of
the world. State charts works the same
way. The idea is you've got the state of
the state chart along with the data that
goes with it. Something happens that
takes the state of the state chart from
one step to another as the mutable
value. So that's that's the general
operational
uh kind of
idea.
And if we look at the if you look at the
guide I even like kind of some
basic examples in here of
machine is not going super fast or
something.
CPUs are all tagged.
Looks like the colonel is doing some
indexing or something. Okay. Um
yeah. So this this little simple traffic
light example in here, right? A state
charge is a declarative thing. It's just
a nested map. Um the nested map actually
gets turned into a uh
kind of a normalized representation sort
of like a fulcro state database uh by
the state chart function. This top level
function here. Oops. To do that
please don't refound.
This uh this top level function here
actually normalizes. What the hell is it
doing?
Oh, this source file is actually here.
It's taking me to the source file that I
included uh in in the ASKI doc. I didn't
actually type that into the ASKI doc.
It's a it's a link to this document.
Um so so state chart here, if you if you
had a ripple running,
I might as well go and run one. Um,
when you make a state chart, it ends up
just being
this data structure
where um
it's got the top level kind of ID of the
state chart itself, which nodes in the
chart are the immediate children of the
root and then a map of elements by ID.
So for every state that has an ID,
here's what the state had in it. And
then the children are referenced by ID.
So instead of it being a tree, like I
said, it's normalized where that's the
ID of a state. Therefore, if I want to
find or a node, if I want to find a
node, I can look it up in this map. Um,
so you can use this like you can use
this data structure to do things like
draw diagrams. That's how that state
chart diagramming thing in folk inspect
works. It actually takes this data
structure, analyzes it, turns it into a
dot or whatever, an elk diagram
just following the edges.
So you got the normalized table there.
Then uh this
uh state charts care about the order
things come in. And so the the state
chart function automatically goes
through and for every node it finds as
it finds it, it gives it a number in
order of reading order. So that's part
of the the specification for state
charts is when you're trying to
distinguish between two things, you
distinguish them in reading order. Like
if you were reading the state chart um
you know at at this level out here uh um
like if there were if there were for
example uh two transitions in this
state, it looks at this one first and
then this one next. So if they both have
the same event, the one with the event
and condition typically, right,
uh that matches first is the one that
taken.
So in document order is a thing.
So that's why there's a table of what
order did this thing come in. So if I'm
having to in the algorithm internally
distinguish between two nodes, I can
figure out which one has precedence.
Um
and then uh this is the this is
basically the sorted list of states,
right? Another way of looking at that
same sort of document order. What order
did these nodes appear in? Uh and so
these are just useful for um uh
implementation detail. So the state
chart is an immutable value. uh and then
the operation of the state chart and and
here simple end jump in here and show
you the some some a basic a really basic
core thing here. The state chart system
uh state charts in general
uh are rather abstract. The standard
that I went from uses XML to define them
and there are a lot of things that are
left left open to the library that
implements the standard. Uh so for
example, when you access data in a state
chart, how do you get to that data?
Where does the data go when it's
running? That's kind of open. It's
open-ended. They don't even tell you how
to structure it. They just say there's
going to be some data and you can kind
of use these following kind of
abstractions to talk about. So I made a
protocol for the data model with the
idea that I don't know how you want to
define your data model. I'll give you a
couple of predefinations, but if you
want to define your own data model,
here's here's what you would need to
implement in the protocol to satisfy the
general constraints.
Uh,
you can send events to state charts.
Well, how do those events get there?
Standard says nothing about that. It
just says you can send an external
event. The external event gets delivered
with some delay. Well, I could use core
async for that. I could use uh uh, you
know, a really simple vector an atom for
that. I could use an SQL database for
that. It's I need to be able to send the
event and then have it somehow get
received. Uh and so the event Q protocol
has a thing that says here's how I want
to send it. Uh here's how I cancel one
that I previously sent because that's
something you have to be able to do uh
in a state chart. You have to be able to
say, oh yeah, that event I scheduled, I
don't want that one anymore. And then
there has to be something that the
implementation itself can use to say all
right I I want to I want to process
events now here's the handler go find
events and tell me what to do.
Uh the execution model has to do with
when you put expressions in the state
chart in the standard it's like yeah you
can put an expression here but what
language is that in? Is it in JavaScript
closure closure script? It turns out the
standard doesn't care and we don't
either. uh if you can give me some sort
of expression
uh and I can define a protocol that can
run that expression then that's all
you'd have to do to make an execution
model for running conditions and scripts
inside of your state chart. It's
completely open-ended.
Uh and then because the standard has
changed over time
uh for processing state charts. So there
was a a standard in 2012 then they
updated it in 2015. That's the most
recent one. They might update it again.
I have a standard in libraries that I
don't break things, right? Um if I if I
upgrade the version, you have to opt
into anything that I do if possible.
There's any way, shape, or form I can
give you uh a new version of the library
without changing anything that you rely
on other than optimizing it or making it
better in a way that won't break your
code. uh they don't want to do that and
so since there's a current standard and
there might be a new standard I defined
the idea of a state chart processor as a
protocol so you can start a state chart
a state chart can exit and a state chart
can process an event and that's the real
working code of you know take the
current you know picture of a state
chart and give me back a new picture of
a new state chart
uh and then this algorithms director
here the current implementation for the
version 201591
is implemented in this namespace.
But if there were a new standard, I
could make a new name space for that new
version and then you could opt into it
by choosing a different processor for
your state charts.
But you could opt into it per state
chart even if you wanted to.
And then there's a protocol for
invocations. So the idea with
invocations is uh a state chart can
start another state chart. And so this
is the the system that would let you
start things of other kinds. They don't
even have to be state charts. It could
start a future. It could start a thread.
It could start some remote process. Um
invocations in state chart are very
abstract. So you can actually make more
than one invocation processor and
install it. Uh and then the state chart
system can scan for those when you say I
want to start this kind of thing. It can
go looking for the processor that can
start that kind of thing. Uh state chart
registry. All right. Well, if you make a
state chart, how does the state chart
system learn about it? You register it.
And so, uh, the registry might be
something that's locally stored in RAM,
might be in a database, wherever you
want to store these, they're just data.
Um, or they can be just data. The way we
use them, we embed lambdas, which are
code, which might have closures. Uh, so
you can't actually store them just
anywhere. They actually do end up
needing to be in a in a RAM registry on
the local server. Uh but let's say you
made uh an execution model that used
JavaScript strings uh for the the
expressions.
Uh well that would make a state chart
completely serializable as data because
your expressions would be strings. Uh
and at that point your state chart
registry could be some global database
somewhere.
And in the working memory store, the
idea here is as you run a state chart.
Uh you've got an immutable value, you
run an event, you get a new immutable
value. Who tracks that? You could just
track it in an atom like we do with the
fog state. Um, but I decided to make a
protocol so you could put something more
complex in front of it and other pieces
of the state chart system could then
leverage that to, you know, pull the
state charts current value, run against
it and then put the new version back.
Uh, so it's a really simple protocol,
right? Get the current version, the
current picture of the running state
chart, uh, save it or if you're done
with it, delete.
Any questions on the idea of the
protocols here? I'm just kind of that's
the sort of theory of operation of the
generics.
>> So the simplest thing you can do
>> go ahead if you have a question.
>> No, I was going to say I think it's
okay.
>> So a simple end uh uses a regular you
know 2015 091 processor.
Uh it uses a standard uh invocation
processor that can only invoke state
charts. Uh oh and it also in in includes
a future processor. So you can invoke
futures. You can start a thread as a
process as an invocation.
Um in CLJ in CLJS there's just the state
chart processor. The execution model is
a lambda based one,
right? So you can use closure
expressions. The event Q is a manually
processed Q, a manually pulled Q. And a
manually pulled Q requires that you
manually run it, right? it doesn't have
any automation in it.
Uh and then the data model I I I set up
by default is is a flat data model where
you just it's as if you just have a map
that you can carry around and you can
see everywhere everywhere in the state
chart. So you can put things in it and
take things out.
So in the traffic lights example, we
make a simple end and so you can just
like make that end. You can register
that. Uh so register is that protocol,
right? Register to state chart and uh
the end as you saw here has keys for all
of these different things, right? The
event Q, uh the working memory, right?
The data model, right? There's a
processor, right? So the im just has
keys for all these implementations of
the protocols needed so that you can
abstractly just say oh well register the
state chart. Okay I want a I want to
pull the processor out of the end and I
could say start the state chart that I
want to call session ID one using the
lights definition right the registered
state chart definition lights. So I
start that and then I get back the
working memory
of that state chart. So these are the
active states,
right? It's running.
It's got this session ID. And if I show
the states there, it's going to just
show me the active states there.
Actually, it's it's changing over time
because this or is it? It shouldn't be.
No, this is just like solid, right? Uh
I'm the show states uh uh eliminates
some of these like parent ones just so
you can see
uh yeah this is a local function this
filters so that I can I only see these
states even though the full set of
active states is this
how many people here yeah yeah yeah
speak up if you do not know what a state
chart is because I'm assuming that
Not
no. Uh I've used uh state machines, but
I don't I don't think I know what a
state chart is.
>> Okay. Well, let's let's go over this
traffic light. It's it's basically if
you know what a state machine is, you're
pretty close. So, a state chart is a
hierarchical state machine.
And in that hierarchy,
multiple states can be active at any
given time. So if this red state is
active then that automatically means its
parent state is active which
automatically means that its parent is
active
right so that's why we're seeing all of
these different active states at a given
time. Ah,
>> now because this is a data structure,
you can very easily write functions to
do parts of your state chart and just
embed them as calls
and it's legal for these functions to
return a vector of states that it'll
just splice into place. So it makes it
really easy to to make things that are a
lot more readable.
So a parallel node allows all of the
immediate children to simultaneously be
active.
So that means this east, west, north,
south, cross, east, west, cross, north,
south are all active at the same time.
And you can see that in the
configuration here of the state chart.
So all four of those are going to be
active and then they're going to be in
some particular state. So what we're
pretending like is we're at right we're
at a normal intersection. There are two
traffic lights for the two different
directions and there are two kinds of
pedestrian signals for the two different
directions and they shouldn't show you
know greens in such a way that
pedestrians get hit by cars.
Right? So we all know how these work. Um
so a pedestrian signal uh starts in an
initial state and that initial state uh
um
ID initial initial
is so this is this is a little function
for making a keyword.
So if you give it you know a keyword and
a string it it does this. If you give it
a existing namespace keyword it extends
the keyword.
So that's what that's doing.
And because I have two different
pedestrian signals, I want crosswalk,
east, west,
uh, and then the name of the initial
state. So this one starts out in red.
This one starts out in white.
So we're going to start one of them in
red, and we're going to start the other
one in white. That's what this initial
parameter is.
Um, and for the traffic signals, we've
got an initial state, which again varies
based on how you write this. East West
starts out green and the crossing east
west starts out red and the traffic for
north south starts out red and the pen
signal for crossing north south starts
out white
and then a transition is basically when
this event happens go to this state when
this event happens go to that state if
I'm in this state
so does that make basic sense
Yes.
>> So states are atomic, right? They they
you can only have in terms of siblings,
you can only have one
uh atomic state active at a time unless
they're embedded in a parallel parent,
which makes all of its immediate atomic
children active simultaneously.
Okay. Now the operation is that I just
got an immutable map that tells me I'm
in that configuration.
If I say process a warn pedestrians
event
on starting state zero, right, this
immutable value here, I'll get the next
state of the state chart. S0 is still
the old value. S1's now the new value.
Right? If I filter out the sort of the
noise, I know I went from
right uh I went from red, white, green,
red to red, flashing white, right? I'm
telling the pedestrians that east north
south is about to have traffic, so you
should think about getting the hell
across the street. Um, if I go to my
next state, S2, now I've got uh flashing
white and the east west traffic light
has turned yellow.
And then if I continue down this like
sequence,
you'll see that the state chart states
one at a time like the working memory
goes from, you know, through the
sequence of of things you would expect
for traffic light operation.
Now the point here is if I'm not storing
uh if I don't have any sort of built-in
loop to do this really I just have to
manually do this right I I have some
particular state chart state uh I run
some event that gives me a new state
start chart state if I don't save that
I've lost it right so you know this mode
of operation is the pure functional mode
of operation right um I'm trying as much
as possible to do pure things. Process
event is actually uh can actually side
effect because your expressions could
side effect. So that's why it's got an
exclamation point on it. But in terms of
the state chart value itself, it is
pure,
right? It's going to you're going to
give it a value. It's going to give you
back a new value. Um well, it's as pure
as it can be because technically your
expressions can change what the state
chart does.
Right. So, it it really isn't completely
pure. Thus, the exclamation point. Um,
but it's as close as possible as I can
get.
Everybody following this?
So, in order to make this system more
usable, let's say you want to use it in
folk. Well, that's going to run in a
browser. So, everything here is CLJC,
right? But obviously the implementation
of the data model, the event cue, you
know, those kinds of things needs to be
something that works well in the browser
and probably isn't persistent
unless I don't know maybe you want to
use browser local storage and store
these things and have your state chart
like start back up as soon as they come
back to the page where it left off,
right? That's actually a possibility.
So that that's why these protocols are
there is you can actually make it work
pretty much any way you want. If you
wanted your state chart storage to be on
the server so that you could restart the
state chart for the user, but it's going
to run in the browser, but it's going to
load its state and save it via, you
know, XHR, you know, JavaScript network
requests. You could do that, right? It's
a really flexible system.
We use it two ways or we set it up two
different ways. On the front end, we
currently only do front-end state charts
that run while the browser session like
that tab is actively running it. If you
reload the tab, you lose the state
chart, right? So the the Q is a core
async object. The working memory data
store is just RAM. Uh the processor is
the normal processor. Uh and then
there's a um this core async event loop.
Uh right. This is basically if you start
this this will this will automatically
deliver events when they're supposed to
be delivered. Uh so we run an a a core
async based event cue on the front end
so that if you send an event and say
yeah wait three minutes before
delivering that event it's actually
handled behind the scenes by core async
behind the protocol.
Uh in fact we use fulcro integration. So
the state charts library has a bunch of
integration name spaces for doing fun
things with state charts in folk
um and and we actually use that. Uh so
when you do the integration here
basically you install it uh where's my
install function
that starts a state chart. Here we go.
So you can install the fake fulcro state
chart stuff on a fulcro app and that
basically installs instances of all the
necessary protocols in the right places.
So that then you can use this function
to start a state chart in your fulcro
app
etc. So you don't have to think about
like what's in the M and how is it
implemented and what have you. You just
you just pass the app to all these
things. Start on my app this state
machine with this session and the
starting data and you're done.
There's also an invocation processor.
The standard invocation processor is
installed, but there's some integration
where you can colllocate a state chart
with a component and have it auto start
uh on routing. That's what this kind of
UI UI route stuff is meant to be. This
is sort of threequarters baked. It's
we're not using it at Dao yet, but uh uh
my intention is to allow you to
eventually be able to build a full-blown
fulkar application by composing state
charts. The top level routes is a state
chart and when you go to some component
in that state chart uh uh the component
itself maybe has a nested state chart
that gets invoked for doing the all the
logic around that module of that of that
route that kind of thing. So that's sort
of where this is headed.
Any questions on the front end thing.
We have numerous examples in the
codebase, but once you understand kind
of the protocol setup, it's not not too
difficult to get the basic idea there.
All good?
>> No questions. Yeah.
>> Okay. So um
how we use this in production backend is
way more interesting and way more kind
of deep.
Um
so you know I've already shown you the
protocol. So essentially what we need to
do if we're going to have closure state
charts um the idea there is well in our
infrastructure we have all sorts of
nodes running. Uh we have compute nodes,
we have UI nodes, we have API nodes. All
those nodes uh are are for things like
high availability, scalability, etc.
A state chart session is a thing, right?
It's a singleton. It's a thing that's
running abstractly in your
infrastructure. So then the question is
who's running it? Is it one of the UI
nodes? Is it a compute node? Is it an
API node? Where like where does it live?
Where's the actual CPU resource that's
running that state chart? Where's its
current state stored like it's config
its current working memory? Like what if
that node crashes that's running it?
Doesn't it memory gets lost? Like how do
we ensure that when we send an event to
a state chart, it actually gets it gets
processed and we keep track of that as
our infrastructure. We do releases right
releases shut down nodes and start new
nodes uh install new versions of the
software uh right it's it's an
interesting distributed system problem
how do I make a state chart system where
my backend which is implemented across
tens sometimes even you know a lot more
than tens but usually tens of nodes tens
20s 30s uh of simultaneous running nodes
how do I make the concept of a running
state chart make sense
Right? If that state chart's providing
something to the user and they're
interacting with the servers, each
request they send is roundroin to a
different server. So this idea that a
state chart is running on a machine that
doesn't work very well. That gets really
really kind of complicated to deal with.
So how do we make that work? Anybody
want to give the guess? Uh no no
cheating. If you already know, don't
don't answer. So does anybody who who
doesn't have an idea want to give a
guess as to how you would do it or how
you would do these different protocols
like here let's just walk through them
right so uh the data model this more has
to do with u
how the data model is is interacted with
for a given state chart so let's let's
skip that one because that that's a
little complicated but an event Q would
deal with an event Q And what I just
described, I've got 10 closure servers.
A user request could be coming from a
browser to any one of the servers. They
might have an existing state chart that
they want to send an event to.
How do I cue that event? And how do I
deliver that event?
Give me some options,
Evan. Give me some options.
Pick on the new guy.
>> Oh, no. Uh,
that is such a good question that I have
no clue.
>> No clue. You don't even have a
suggestion. Like if we were implementing
this, I was like, Evan, we got this. I
need to run a state chart. I need some
sort of event Q that can multiple nodes
can access and
uh I can send events and receive them on
any node. like
>> oh SQS, SNS,
uh Kafka, talking about like a durable
Q.
>> All right. So yeah, we need some sort of
durable queue. Um
>> okay, now I'm going to add an additional
constraint. When I deliver an event, I
have to make sure that the the event is
delivered exactly once
in the face of the algorithm crashing
right in the middle because of a node
shutdown.
Um
I mean item potency
>> I guess does it it needs to be delivered
exactly once or it needs to action needs
to be taken on it exactly once.
>> Well we we can't have there's no way for
us to make sure that uh any side effects
that expressions in the state chart
there's no way for us to ensure that
those might not happen more than once.
We actually can't make that guarantee
because we might have to we might
>> get halfway through running the event
and the node crashes
>> which means we could have done some side
effects. So let's assume that the state
chart expressions we know as programmers
that if you write a state chart
expression it must if it's side effects
it must be an item potent side effect.
>> Yep.
>> Okay. So so we're okay there. We don't
have to worry about that. We do have to
worry about it. We have to document and
let every developer know you better be
doing item potent expressions.
>> Okay, but think about the thing that's
actually happening. I've got an event.
I'm going to uh I'm going to pull that
off the queue. I want to make sure that
if I pull it off the queue, nobody else
can pull off the queue. SQS would be
good for that.
>> Yeah.
>> But that if I go to run it, um uh I've
got to load the current view of what's
in the state chart. I've got to run the
state chart against that to get the new
value. Now I have to write that back to
the storage.
>> And now I have to say the event is been
delivered and remove the event from the
queue.
>> Yep.
>> Okay. Now what do you feel like we need
as a requirement?
>> Any any does that help any?
Um,
I guess my first thought is that
and I I'd have to look up the specifics,
but I'm pretty sure that SQS
has a like you pull for um
>> a message
>> and it will hide it from every other
consumer for a certain period of time.
And you have to send um a response that
says all right this message has been
handled.
>> Yeah.
>> And then it will that gives you the
>> for extended time. Yes.
>> Yeah. That gives you the event the event
manipulation but you're missing the big
problem. The big pro here. Let me give
you some scenarios. I pull I pull a
message from SQS. I've got a visibility
timeout. I've got some time to process
it.
>> I pull the current state of the state
chart. It says my traffic lights are in
such and such a state.
Right? I run the state chart. It gives
me the new version of the traffic
lights. Now the node crashes.
Okay. The event gets redelivered to me.
>> Okay, that's all good. I think I think
that that case works. Okay. Right.
>> Um
uh
now let's say I do that same scenario. I
pull it. I run it. I save it.
and the node crashes.
>> Now the that event's going to get
redelivered, but I have already saved
the effect of that event to my working
storage for the state chart.
So in other words, there was a way for
me to undo the fact that I actually did
the event.
>> Yeah. and the state in a new state as
far as the system is concerned.
>> Um
first thought is
in the saved state
either in the event itself or in the
saved state. So when um the node is
going to pull the current state chart
inside of there, there's some way to
say, "Oh, this event has already been
handled. The state chart you've pulled
covers this event."
>> Um and could be
>> Yeah. What if it's a high frequency
state chart that gets 100 events per
second?
That doesn't work very well.
So you make you make whatever is like
whatever the event like the handle of
the event item potent right and that way
you
>> well but how do you make it item that's
the problem that's the problem that
we're trying to solve here right I just
gave you a case where right because
you're doing each individual right
you're on a computer you're doing each
individual instruction one at a time
>> right yes
>> you pull the state you run the state
chart you save the state you delete the
event from the queue
Right?
>> If you fail to delete the event from the
queue, then the event will get
redelivered. In fact, it could get
redelivered anyway
uh uh in this particular scenario and
that would actually be bad, right? We
want we want exactly want semantics
which means
uh right so so
the Q as implemented
>> you would have to make what what Evan's
talking about right you'd have to make
the only way to make that truly item
potent is to track is to give a UYU ID
to each event
>> and track every event you've delivered
by its ID
>> right
>> but how do you save the fact that you
that you did it what if the node crashes
as you're trying to save the fact that
you did it, but you've already done it.
>> If you try to save it before you do it
to make sure you saved it, then what
happens if it crashes and you don't do
it?
>> Can you have an identification of the
every state that you have? So as you do
a mutation you get a new like you had
like in your example you had s0 s1 s2
>> and for each of those you have a
identification for it
>> and so it's what I'm trying to say is
kind of like a cast situation.
>> Yeah.
>> So I'm doing um this UID event on this
UID state
>> and therefore if I kind of lose track of
one or the other I don't perform the
operation. I don't know.
>> That's an interesting idea, right? So
then so yeah, so his basic idea is I'll
I'll I'll do some sort of Cass operation
where I say
>> uh I expect the state chart to to be in
in at this point in time basically.
>> Um and you could just do a time stamps.
You could do a CAS with time stamps. I
assume that the state chart hasn't had a
an event delivered since this time.
>> I'll do all the steps. I'll try the CAS.
If the CAS fails, then I'll undo things.
you still have the problem of who undoes
things if the node is crashed you can't
undo anything
>> my thought on so
part of this I think would be splitting
up so one part is okay if we store it in
the state but there's a lot of rights a
thought is okay incorporate something
like dynamob or some other like high
throughput thing where you're going to
record
um the event ID if there's a meaningful
identifier for the state chart like
maybe the event it doesn't matter what
like the event doesn't care what the
state chart is we care not to re run the
event but the event itself the actual
functioning it's going to do doesn't
care and then you have timestamps for
like began processing at be and you know
finished processing at began
>> and however and the number of time
stamps you would have would be whatever
granularity
would make would like fit with the
architecture for
we can
get through like the like whatever would
make sense for checkpointing like
essentially be a checkpointing like okay
I've begun processing and then the First
step that this event needs me to do is
go fetch some data. So I'm recorded that
the state chart has begun processing and
then I recorded that it went to fetch
some data and then I record when that
data came back and then I like doing
that kind of granularity
and you can't have infinite granularity
um per se just because of physics but uh
>> well this just it so so I I wrote these
comments down to help define the problem
for you
>> right
>> so the semantics of This must be that
events are delivered exactly once,
right? That's the guarantee that that
external users want, right?
>> And we're must be
>> we're going to put a quick
>> we're going to put a constraint on this
sort of like swap note to devs
uh expressions
must be item potent,
>> right? As long as your expressions are
item potent, we will give you a
guarantee that it looks like your events
are delivered exactly once. That's the
guarantee we're trying to provide. But
it needs to be a 100% never fails
absolutely totally guaranteed true,
>> right? And the sequence of event
processing
is what you just saw in this traffic
lights thing, right? We we basically
read the old version, run the event, get
the new version and then we have to save
that somewhere,
right? So this is like load s0 run save
s1 mark event delete, you know, mark
event, you know,
>> so that's that's that's essentially what
I'm I'm trying to get to here.
And so right now if there's a failure
here
I have actually this side affected and
saved I have actually delivered the
event but I've lost the fact that I've
delivered the event and now I get at
least once semantics. That's not
acceptable.
>> If I try to flip these
then I get at most once semantics. I
might actually miss an event
because I've I've failed to save the
fact that the event that the events
effect on the state chart.
>> What is this smack up? I'm surprised.
>> Positive.
>> What's that?
>> It's a false positive. But no, I I
like
whatever operation you do, there will
always be a chance that something fails.
So I I don't really know. Yeah, but
there's a computer there's a whole field
of computer science that has to do with
this exact problem.
>> You talking about um two generals.
>> No, that's distributed systems uh trying
to decide. Yeah, you you can if you do
this wrong, you end up with two generals
and you can never solve it,
>> right?
>> Yeah,
>> that's that's if you do this wrong. But
there's a whole area of computer science
that that deals with uh operations that
need to happen together.
Ah, so like
Miguel raised his hand like a like a
transa like some sort of like indexing
or transaction.
>> I was going to say but I I don't know if
you wanted to
keep them guessing.
>> No, I don't want to keep guessing. I
want I want people to realize that this
is the right this is this is the thing.
And in fact
uh
>> so how do you make stuff in transaction
when when it's different systems?
>> Good question. How do you
>> I I don't know.
>> You use SQL.
>> You use an SQL database.
>> Ah so I'm going to use SQL. Okay. I'm
going to use the transactionability of
SQL for everything.
>> Exactly. Use database like datomic or
SQL. use something that has acid
compliant transactions.
Uh, which is why this this item potency
thing like like the transaction may
cause you to do it more than once, but
it guarantees that it either all
succeeds or all fails.
So, as long as your side effects are
item potent, it fixes this problem.
So,
So then are you grabbing events from
SQL?
>> Yep.
>> Then we've seen this in detail.
There's our protocol. Here's our
implementation in SQL.
>> So there's a listener that's always
waiting for event to happen.
>> Receive event.
uh there's a loop that runs we start a
thread actually we start threads on
multiple nodes so that's another aspect
of this if there are lots of state
charts running you want lots of threads
processing events
>> true yeah
>> right so you actually start a bunch of
threads and all those threads in a loop
call receive events
and each of those runs a transaction
>> I thought we use cq for this. Yeah,
that's cool.
>> No, this is SQL.
>> Yeah, cool. I didn't know that
>> because of this issue,
>> right? And this selecting uh whether or
not an event is delivered, right? So,
give me uh uh for a given event. So,
this question mark is uh on an ID. So, I
I I I find some event.
>> Sure.
>> Right. Which is this find next best
event. This is a little this is an extra
little algorithm for the SQL database
which looks in the event queue for
anything that's supposed to have been
triggered already and hasn't been
delivered.
Now, because I'm running 40 different
threads that are processing events, I
may get the same events as some other
node. Now, we're in a race. Who's going
to deliver that event?
Right? And so, there's some there's some
kind of logic in here and then some
shuffle, right? Right. There's some
randomization to try to make sure nodes
don't always pick the same events and
fight over them.
>> Um,
>> trigger implies that the event was sent
or that someone grabbed it.
>> Trigger time is when you're supposed to
deliver because you can delay an event.
You can say, I want this subscription
event delivered a month from now.
>> Ah,
>> right. So trigger time is is the time
stamp at which you want the event
delivered.
If you don't delay it, that's now.
So ID is a name and data source end ID.
This is so fancy. I had never seen this
code. So we're looking for things where
the trigger time is before now. Right.
It's supposed to have been triggered
already.
>> Yes.
>> It's not been delivered.
>> Okay.
>> Right. And then we'll create an event
data structure out of that.
Um
>> and then we're fighting each other to to
to finish the transaction first.
>> Exactly. But we shuffle them if there's
more than one. Sorry. If there's a
desired target. I don't know what that I
don't remember what this logic's about,
but this shuffle logic is just trying to
keep two nodes from picking the same
event so that they conflict,
>> right? Um, and so we find the next best
event and then we select the delivered
field from that true or false
for that particular event ID and we lock
it. So in SQL this says lock that row so
nobody else can can proceed from here.
>> Right? Right.
>> Will the last guy not grab lock things?
>> No. Everybody tries to grab the lock for
this row and only one will get it.
>> Ah, okay. Okay. Okay. Okay. Okay. Okay.
>> It turns out in multiszone
AWS, this doesn't always work.
So, so we also have this little reddus
double check to make sure that two nodes
don't run the same event at the same
time.
>> Okay. So we're looking in radius and
SQL.
>> Yeah. So we do a double lock on it
actually.
>> It's not really a transaction is it? If
we're doing ready is there.
>> It's kind of transaction.
>> I don't want to talk about this
particular element of it. I still just
pretend this works. Right.
>> Okay.
>> Right. I've locked the event. So I know
now I'm the only transaction that can
touch that event. And then I set it to
delivered but I'm in a transaction. And
I run the handler which you've handed me
which does the state chart operations
right it does the read the update the
save right but all those are SQL
operations right because the working
storage protocol is also implemented in
the same SQL database
right so the um there's the event Q
event handling component chart
where's my other
Um,
>> so then the handler won't happen in the
transaction.
>> No, the handler happens in the
transaction. We're in the transaction.
>> Yes.
>> Handler gets the database transaction
connection.
>> Sure.
>> Right. Um, and then this handler for
state charts here. Let's go back to
where this this is.
>> So we cannot side effects, right? that
>> as long as they're item potent side
effects, you can,
>> right? That's the thing we we talked
about just a minute ago.
SQL. Where's my handler?
Receive one event handler. That's that
handler. Oh, right. When you call
receive events, you hand it the handler.
Um, so I I don't remember where it's at
right now. Uh but the there is a
um
if we look for where this is used we'll
find where the whole thing is set.
>> Uh I don't sleep.
>> Here we go.
Right. So here's the here's the event
durable event threads
um and the event loop step. So we we
start a task processor with some number
of threads that can be configured in the
config file and this event loop step uh
calls receive events. Uh handle event
type is a multimethod.
Um
yeah so there's actually more pieces to
this than I remembered. Uh so handle
event types of multimethod and then the
multimethod
for handling state charts
right landmark on it uh right takes the
database connection which is the SQL
connection that's in a transaction
>> right
>> right um and pulls the working session
memory right so this is this is that uh
calls that protocol method get working
memory and in the working memory uh uh
for this guy
in
the working memory store. Sorry, this is
a lot of stuff is an SQL working memory
store.
>> So you save working memory, you give it
a connection which going to be in the
transaction. Uh right. So to get it, it
pulls it and deserializes it. And to
save it, it serializes it and then puts
it in the SQL database.
>> So this can all be in the same
transaction,
>> right? So if the transaction fails, it
undoes any update to the state chart.
So that's that's kind of the glue that
makes this all work is the SQL database
is an acid compliant way of ensuring
that we can pull the event update the
event to mark it delivered pull the
state machine state update it and resave
it all as a unit.
I have I have a question
multiple threads.
>> If for some reason we have I don't know
let's say the working memory store in a
different database that wouldn't work.
Right.
>> Would not work. Correct.
>> Okay.
>> Correct. You would lose the
transactional consistency.
Part of the reason why I'm going over
this in such like you know
>> painful
uh uh detail is exactly that this this
is actually a hard problem. Um
like
>> so how do we handle subscriptions then?
>> Subscriptions are a state chart.
>> Yes.
>> And right they you deliver events to
them. The events are delayed like the
the expiration of a of a subscription is
the delayed delivery of a of an
expiration event.
>> Right. Right. Right.
>> They've got a month. We we immediately
send a month-long delayed event that
says expired.
>> Sure.
But then when will like when will
like so since subscriptions or like
we're getting that information from
datomic like how are we handling the two
databases? ah datomic is tracked it is
datomic uh we we do item potent
operations against datomic
in our expressions
>> right so for example if if we notice in
the state chart that we've expired
uh we go to a state if you go and look
at this the subscription state chart is
our most complicated state chart
>> yes
Here
you go.
>> This this state chart is
uh
>> yeah it's fun
>> is 248 lines where all of the
expressions have been put in a different
name space. So this is just the
structure of the chart.
>> Yes.
>> Right. So it's a it's a rather large
chart. Uh so for example let's say that
you're in the the paid state.
>> Sure.
Wherever the paid state is
these unpaid
I thought we had a separate oh here we
go state paid right so in this state you
can receive a an expiration event
>> and the target
>> is expired with renew
>> if their auto renew is turned So if auto
renew is turned on, basically we're just
going to send them a new invoice
immediately, right? Uh and try to update
their plan. If they don't have auto
renew, then we send them to inactive.
Um
uh so expired with renew. Oops.
I guess where I was getting to is is
this the state chart is sort of written
in some cases to kind of self-heal.
Uh so for example, if they say, "Oh, I
want to renew my uh subscription. Um,
and it turns out that we had screwed up
and hadn't like kept track of it right.
Maybe they've already paid us. Uh, when
they go into the uh unpaid state as you
enter the unpaid state, uh, I thought,
oh, we've added HubSpot into this. Yeah.
So, there's like other tracking in here.
Uh,
basically there's some elements in here
like I'm pretty sure there's a choice
element in here. Yeah. Um so this node
basically is just a a group of
transitions that is always checked in
this state
and if this expression is true it moves
you here otherwise it moves you to
there. Um I'm sorry if you get if you
get sent to the unpaid condition right
so if we get a payment made event it
sends you here and see it says all right
well we got a payment uh do we are we
fully paid for? If so, we go to paid
otherwise uh we we'll go to the grace
period state.
>> So I guess I I guess the thing that I'm
trying to to say in answer to your
question is
>> um the the expressions in these state
charts have to be item potent and then
sometimes you need to write in logic
that that checks the real underlying say
datomic database and makes makes
decisions on where to go in the state
chart on that. That's not because of
lost events. It's it's because of the
exact problem you're talking about. The
datomic database may actually not be in
sync with where the state lives,
>> right?
>> Yeah.
>> And so support has things like like if
you reset this state chart and start it
over the expressions and the conditions
that are startup conditions of the state
chart will naturally move you to the
right state.
So, so if we look at the startup here of
this, like if we go to the the very
>> Yeah, there's like initial a big initial
condition. There you go. Line 205.
>> Yeah, it goes to the start condition and
says, "Oh, well, if you've got a paid
plan, go to paid. If you're in a grace
period, go to grace. If you're in a
note, right?" So, this kind of checks
the datic database so that if you're
just starting this a new, you could just
delete the state chart altogether. You
could lose it. You could crash whatever.
Day datomic is the database of record of
what you
>> the source of truth
>> with invoices, right?
>> Yeah.
>> So
>> yeah, that that answers my question.
>> So that's
>> but then we we don't fully have the like
the fully item code and transaction cool
thing where we can like just trust on
our state charts forever. Like we do
have this and like this will just save
us in case. Well, what we've got is if
you have a state chart that does not
side effect,
uh, we have exactly one semantics and
it'll just work, right? We do have that
because all that'll be in the SQL
database. But yeah, as soon as you want
it coordinating external processes,
well, yeah, now you've got this concern
of
>> is my external process actually
synchronized with my state chart?
>> Did the external thing happen?
Basically,
>> question mark. Yeah. Because somebody
could have paid you and you know for
whatever reason
>> Yeah. payment state time or whatever.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Like weird things can happen
and you just want to be able to to heal
it and um and so having the state chart
written because the state chart is
really a way to organize your logic so
that you can think about the problem
clearly because this is a very complex
process. Before we were using state
charts,
>> our subscription system was a nightmare
uh to handle and it was very simple. it
had like one tenth of the features that
this has or less actually less had maybe
five% of the features and you still
couldn't understand.
Um and so the state chart's a great way
to organize the logic of exactly what
should happen and why and where and what
have you. So you can reason over it, you
can draw a diagram of it. Um, but it is
true that that even though that logic is
well structured and you can understand
it, that doesn't mean you know you're
not going to run into problems like you
just said like the datomic database is a
separate database.
>> Even if it was transactional, what if
you'd sent what if you side effected and
sent the invoice to the Dion? You can't
just forget it.
>> Right.
>> There's another external system that you
have to synchronize with that you just
can't put in your transaction. You can't
say, "Oh, Dion, I want two-phase
commit." You know,
if I manage to commit my transaction,
then pretend like you saw, you know. Um,
all right. Where we at?
That's the hardest part of the system to
understand is there's actually an SQL
table um that you can in your local uh
you know, local host
utility.
Right. There's the table
done. That's cool.
>> Right. And
here's your store,
>> right? So there's your running state
machine state as be, you know, bite
array encoded Eden.
>> So cool.
>> Yeah. And then we even implemented, we
don't really use this anymore. Support
was sort of abusing it.
>> Um,
uh,
>> but there's a paused flag.
>> Yeah.
>> On the state machine state.
>> So you can indicate that you want a
state machine to not accept events. So
that if you're trying to debug
something, you can actually pause the
state chart and the event delivery
system, if it sees this flag set to
true, just like
>> just doesn't deliver the event and
leaves the leaves the leave it marked.
>> Somebody got their mic unmuted and
somebody's talking.
>> Sorry. Yeah, it's me, Valentina.
>> That's Valentina.
>> Let me close the door.
So um so yeah the the way we use them is
actually fairly complicated and the
startup um most of our most of our
thread startup happens in the server
component the middle middleware server
component. Um,
and so cute thread start durable event
threads. So here's where we actually
start all the threads on a GI on all the
nodes basically based on our
configuration.
So I can default Eden
you know there's some number of threads
for the durable event Q
and so you can you can configure that
right.
And when we construct the actual
environment for our state chart running,
we put in all those implementation of
those protocols that use the SQL
database so that we can do this
transactional thing and make sure
everything's delivered well.
So kind of fun.
In fact, this this flexibility I sort of
like I've noticed that most of my
libraries aren't terribly popular
>> in the in the even though they're open
sourced.
>> Uh some people get them and some people
don't. But I think part of the
difficulty that people have with my
libraries in general is I use the same
functional paradigm. But I tend to leave
a lot of like flexibility in the
implementation
so that you can do cool complex things
like this. Um but then I don't open
source my like you know AWS specific SQL
event cue for people to use. And so, you
know, people want a turnkey solution and
it's it's not turnkey except for folk.
You can do front end fulcro without
having to write anything.
Anyway, so what other questions did
people have about state charts coming
into this that maybe they've wondered
about that they'd like me to talk about?
We're over time, but I feel like since
we just kind of got to the
through the this is how how it's hooked
together. Maybe maybe people have some
other questions about them that they
wanted answered and didn't
>> I have one
>> I I would like to know how to draw
charts
>> like I know that we can do diagrams but
I
>> we have no way of doing those. We have
no way of doing those because there was
a conflict between the libraries and we
never upgraded it. conflict library
>> like we we were up upgrading our state
chart our state chart version in the tso
and something failed and we just
immediately stopped it.
>> Yeah, we can we can attempt to do that.
I haven't I've only written I've written
two different sort of versions of trying
to make state charts something you can
have an automated diagram built of.
>> Um
and is in the state charts library
itself in the dev folder
this xstate namespace
um and this is halfbaked but you could
grab this source code and tinker with it
so there's a there's a javascripty
library out here that does state charts
called xate
and
they have a visualizer
>> um that you You know, if if you put it
in this JavaScripty format,
uh, then you can how do you
how do you view it? I forget how to how
you actually visualize. There we go.
It'll draw a nice diagram for you.
Um, and since this does follow the same
state chart standard, technically you
can trans translate R Eden into J this
JavaScript format and then dump it in
here and see it.
Okay.
>> And so that's what this this would this
works on simple simple ones.
Uh like like here like if I
load this name space and dump this this
will give me you know something I can
translate into JSON.
>> Yeah.
>> Console log cl.js. That should be JSON.
Thought you're not CJD.
>> What am I What am I messing up here,
guys? Shouldn't that be
>> Isn't it because you're in a closure
ripple instead of
>> Yeah. So, if you do this in closure
script and then copy this and paste it
into that thing, you'll get a diagram.
>> Uh the the problem that you run into
with translating them is the
expressions.
out of the state chart have to be turned
into something JavaScripty and so you
end up need to put little stubs in like
here
right where I'm putting in you know
stubs for the different functions that
it would want to call and you can't use
lambdas so our our the state chart that
this one because we don't we just use
symbols here
um
uh I I think technically you could
translate this fairly simply. So that's
one way. That's one approach,
>> right? Is is just use just steal this
code out of the state charts GitHub
repository and hack on it. It's not that
long, right? Uh it's 100 lines of code
or 150.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. So you could probably make this
work and then you get this really
beautiful, you know, thing that you can
like, you know, click on and watch
things flow and what have you, right?
Um
>> yes that's one way of doing it. The
other way is the way I've done it in
folk inspect uh which some you know most
of you have sort of seen there's a tab
in f fulcro inspect where you can go to
the state charts and pick a front-end
state chart that doesn't help you with
backend
but
uh so these are these are open source
contributions nudge nudge hint hint
so here's what I've already done in the
visualization I made a CLJS visualizer
and this code goes through
and converts
uh a state chart into
uh DOM
and then uses uh this is called the uh
Eclipse layout kernel kernel Elk and it
turns out there's a JavaScript version
of this library and a Java version of
this library
and what it will do for you is it will
position the nodes for you. It'll find a
layout, right? If you give it a thousand
nodes with all the connections, it'll
try to figure out a good layout for
those for you, right? Which is actually
a very difficult computer science
problem.
So turning them into DOM nodes is easy.
And then Elk makes it gives you back the
coordinates you should put them at,
right? Um and so I've this is what
Fulcro is currently using. Folk inspect
is this, you know, Fulcrobased
visualizer component
that uses
hooks that I wrote, right? So, render
edges makes an SVG uh for drawing the
lines and then it it puts the DOM
elements on top of it.
Um,
and then in order to get the elk layout,
where is the elk layout? Yeah, use elk
layout. I made a a react use effect hook
that would call the asynchronous layout
function of elk, get back the layout,
set the layout so that then the UI
updates its draw.
Okay, there is a Java version of this
library and I started to implement it
here that has basically the same API and
it's it's really a translation of the
Java code to JavaScript that gives you
the JavaScript version.
And so if you want a closure-based
visualizer,
>> I'm close.
I just haven't finished it.
It's kind of the same basic structure.
You set the options, you get the layout,
and then you would use something like, I
don't know, make a JF frame or right
here I'm I'm uh still doing DOM and
render to string. So then you could just
like load that in a browser, right? Um
as HTML, that was one idea. Or you could
use a JFrame and try to draw the stuff
in a Java window. Uh
>> yeah,
>> but the hard part is the layout. The
layout's done for you by this library.
Uh, and so somebody just needs to go in
here and finish this. I haven't I
haven't finished it.
So if you wanted a good open source
contribution to the state charts
library, uh, there's the answer to your
question. How do you graph it? Basically
like this.
Who's up? I don't see the hand raising.
>> No, Evan Evan left the comment. uh to
use.
>> Yeah, I put I said Java FX maybe and I
feel like Donsky Nikita Donssky is got
um a visualizer
be awesome,
>> right?
>> I think there's a
>> what is it called?
>> Like it would be awesome to have a
visualizer for portal.
>> Yeah.
So the other thing that I thought to do
because I've got the visualizer in folk
inspect is if you add a well-known path
ohm resolver where I can say give me the
state chart definition over the network
then we could make the front end fulcr
inspect query the backend for your state
chart sessions and you could just pick
one or autocomplete it and then show it
in folk inspect
that's another idea
>> which would be even cooler it would be
cooler that would be awesome
>> test production
So you could do it against dev or
production or whatever.
>> Yeah.
>> So
that's the answer to that question.
And it would be really nice to have the
drawing. That's part of the reason why I
wanted to move to state charts, right?
Is that it's easy to think about you can
and you can draw it. If you can draw it,
way easier to talk about it, right?
Point to that, point to that. Like
the the
>> Yeah, you can reason about it. You can
just like this is the subscription state
chart.
>> Yeah.
>> And it's easier.
>> So I mean the you know the state chart
structured data thing it's it's sort of
a drawing right you you can kind of like
you know look around on it but yeah an
actual drawing would be more convenient
in a lot of cases.
>> We didn't really find the bug right with
the library with the stitcher library.
>> I don't know. We could that that could
be a I mean suggest that as a a thing in
retros like Maybe we should do this to
get visualizations of state charts
>> because then we could draw them and it'd
be so cool.
>> Yep.
>> Other questions?
>> So what happened in Shaki's case that um
I think spurred the whole thing was that
the the SQL database was plotted. Is
that it?
>> No, she had So your SQL database is in
Docker. It's persistent. So it had
durable events in the event queue that
had not been delivered that were tied to
a particular session ID that no longer
existed in Daytonic.
So when she started her system up, it
went to deliver those events, went to
find the state chart session, found a
session, but then it referred to company
ids that weren't in the datomic
database.
>> So then it couldn't find a database. So
then it gave her null pointer
exceptions.
>> That's interesting.
>> Oh, but isn't it an SQL inmemory
database when we're doing develop? No,
>> it's
>> you can set it up either way you want,
right? You can set it up as H2 which
would prevent that problem,
but we we I think I recently either I
did or somebody did.
>> Oh, that's what happened. Yeah,
>> we changed it. Yeah,
>> I think we recently changed this. So, it
used um
>> the the actual database.
>> Yeah, utility. You're right. We used to
do an H2 database here and that's
probably why.
Yeah, that's why nobody else had the
problem up until now.
>> Yeah, we just did this a few days ago.
That's why
>> we could just clean up clean up like
when we see we could clean up. It would
still
>> I had not fast enough, right?
>> I had Shaki add code to the refresh
caches when you seed that deletes all
the rows.
>> But it would still not be fast enough,
right? Because like you we don't see it
fast enough when we start the server. So
it would
>> the strap would still try to do things.
It could
>> before we see.
>> Yeah, it could.
>> Sorry, I didn't follow. What is the
utility um on line 57?
>> That's where the that's the database
that's used for the durable event QE and
the state chart working memory,
>> right? And what we changed was line 58.
Is that it?
>> Uh yeah, what we what we changed was uh
to use Postgress instead of H2 for this
database.
>> Ah okay.
So,
>> so if I if I look at this uh
I can draw.
>> Oh, it's not showing me the right
diffic.
>> I thought I was on the right commit.
>> No, that's not right. Right. change the
mode to use plus double click on it and
you have to you have to slide the the
bottom right window more to the left. Oh
yeah.
And that
>> I would love to draw but I don't know.
Wait, we can Google.
>> There's this very small death on the
bottom right like I was saying.
>> Yeah. Bottom right has
>> Oh, all right. Thank you.
>> Would love to draw. I feel I think I
know I can. Yeah. Okay. There you go.
>> Yeah. No, you click on that.
>> That's
Yeah. So see it used to be an H2
database which is just in memory and so
when you restarted that just got wiped
out every time.
>> I see
>> I switched it here so you could actually
look at it easily with Psql or some
other database utility if you wanted to.
>> What's that?
>> God is gooey man.
>> All right. Any more any more questions?